Jean Ritchie and George Pickow collection
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Subseries 2: Performances, lectures, and workshops
    - Sub-subseries 4: Awards, films, instruments, itineraries, recordings, and workshops
      - Scripts, 1959-1993 (Box-folder 56/4)
        A script from Jean's 1963 radio show, "As I Roved Out," a transcript of Jean's 1993 interview for the Port Washington Public Library's Centennial Oral History Project, a script for Oscar Brand's "Song of Nassau" (1976), a handwritten script, routine sheets from the Dave Garroway show (1959), and related documents.
      - "Old Music For New Ears" (series, 1991-1992 (Box-folder 56/5)
        Schedules, information for the teleprompter, song lists, texts for song introductions, and related documents.
      - "Aunt Jenny's Real Life Stories" (CBS): "Prettiest Girl in Town," 1949 (Box-folder 56/6)
        Correspondence and a partial script.
      - James Hardiman Library (Box-folder 56/7)
        Correspondence, newspaper clippings, and other ephemera relating to the Library's acquisition of the Ritchie-Pickow collection in 1996.
      - Cecil Sharp project, 1982-1990 (Box-folder 56/8)
        Correspondence and a project proposal relating to a proposed project to honor Cecil Sharp, which culminated in an exhibit and presentations at the National Museum of American History, Smithsonian Institution: "The Legacy of Cecil Sharp: Country Dance and Song in America" (a program is also in the folder).
      - Jean Ritchie Endowed Chair in Rural Social Work (University of Kentucky), 1980-2000 (Box-folder 56/9)
        Dinner program celebrating the 10th anniversary of the Master of Social Work degree at the University of Kentucky, documents relating to fundraising for the endowed chair and alumni response forms filled out by Jean, and two newsletters published by the College of Social Work alumni.
      - Fulbright trip and activities (1/2), 1950-1967 (Box-folder 56/10)
        Materials relating to Jean's Fulbright trip, including a grant application, correspondence, a newspaper clipping, documentation on recordings, a Covent Garden ballet season program, and related documents. A photo has been relocated to Series 3.
      - Fulbright trip and activities (2/2), 1950-1967 (Box-folder 56/11)
        See the description for box-folder 56/10.
      - Trip to England, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 56/12)
        A list of cabin passengers, correspondence, a pass for the coronation of Queen Elizabeth II. Newspaper clippings, maps, and related documents.
      - Correspondence about England, 1953 (Box-folder 57/1)
        Correspondence
      - Trip to the British Isles (1/2), 1952-1954 (Box-folder 57/2)
        A list of cabin passengers (with a pencilled annotation), correspondence, travel information and ephemera, maps, car registration information, a press pass (probably for George), Jean's certificate of registration as an alien (including a photo of her), and other ephemera.
      - Trip to the British Isles (2/2), 1952-1954 (Box-folder 57/3)
        See the description for box-folder 57/2.
      - Irish trip, 1952-1954 (Box-folder 57/4)
        Correspondence, permissions for George to take photos in various settings and circumstances, a copy of Spin magazine (vol. 3, no. 1), brochures, and related ephemera.
      - Trip to England, 1966-1968 (Box-folder 57/5)
        Correspondence, ticket stubs, and handwritten notes.
      - Western journey, 1975, 1977 (Box-folder 57/6)
        Correspondence, invoices, an performance agreement between Jean and Golden West College, a performance agreement between Jean and McCabe's (1975), another agreement for performances and a workshop (1977), and related ephemera.
      - Awards (1/3), 1967-2009 (Box-folder 57/7)
        Correspondence, programs, brochures, certificates conveying honors, National Heritage Fellowship event information (2002), a photo of Jean receiving an honorary doctorate at the University of Kentucky, a stock certificate, prints, a commencement booklet (2008), a newspaper clipping, a reprint of Cavalier magazine (1965), and related ephemera.
      - Awards (2/3), 1967-2009 (Box-folder 58/1)
        See the description for box-folder 57/7.
      - Awards (3/3), 1967-2009 (Box-folder 58/2)
        See the description for box-folder 57/7. Photos have been relocated to Series 3.
      - Various items, 1955-1963 (Box-folder 58/3)
        Items received with the 2013 accrual. A newspaper clipping, correspondence, a photo, and other items. The photo has been relocated to Series 3.
    - Sub-subseries 5: Programs and posters
      Materials in this sub-subseries are organized by event (when possible) and approximate size. These include programs from various events and concerts, in the form of handbills, flyers, announcements, tickets, invitations, and one item of correspondence. Box 61 is an oversized flat document box. Container 62 is a flat oversized folder, holding three items. Two lanyards have been relocated to Series 5 (Artifacts): a performer pass for the White River Folk Festival, and an all-access pass for "Rosalie Sorrels and Her Friends," from 2002.
      - Group 1, 1976-2007 (Box-folder 58/4)
        Programs from the Kentucky Music Weekend, in Louisville. Includes a program from the first event in 1976 (Jean wrote "1974?" on the front cover; the cover is inscribed by Asa Martin to Jean), as well as programs from 1979, 1980, 1982, 1985, 1986, 1989, 1992, 2004, 2006, and 2007.
      - Group 2, 1980-2004 (Box-folder 58/5)
        Christmas Revels: flyer (1993) and programs (1980, 1985, 1986, 1992-1994, 1996, 2000, and 2004)
      - Group 3, 1981-2007 (Box-folder 58/6)
        Appalachian Family Folk Week brochures from 1981, 1984, 1987-1988, 1992-1993, 2003-2005, and 2007.
      - Group 4, 1963-2006 (Box-folder 58/7)
        Tickets, passes, and a sticker from various events and venues. Includes Jean's festival staff member/family cafeteria card while she was at the Sixth Annual Berkeley Folk Music Festival (1963).
      - Group 5, 1961-2007, undated (Box-folder 58/8)
        Handbills, invitations, and announcements (with some duplicate copies) for various events and venues.
      - Group 6, 1951-1982, undated (Box-folder 58/9)
        Brochures and announcements for various events and venues.
      - Group 7, 1950, 1959 (Box-folder 58/10)
        Programs for contemporary music festivals (Columbia University, 1950 and Hofstra College, 1959).
      - Group 8, 1971, 1978, 1993, 2004 (Box-folder 58/11)
      - Group 9, 1964-1966 (Box-folder 58/12)
        Programs for The Kingdom Come Swappin' Meetin'. An undated program may be from 1968.
      - Group 10, 1979-2002 (Box-folder 58/13)
        Programs for dulcimer-oriented events.
      - Group 11, 1967-1974 (Box-folder 58/14)
        Programs from Pinewoods Camp Folk Music Week.
      - Group 12, 1961-1990, undated (Box-folder 59/1)
        Catalogs, a schedule, and promotional materials.
      - Group 13, 1950-2006, undated (Box-folder 59/2)
        Programs, brochures, and related materials (some duplicate copies).
      - Group 14, 1952-2003 (Box-folder 59/3)
        See the description for box-folder 59/2.
      - Group 15, 1950-2007 (Box-folder 59/4)
        Flyers, announcements, brochures, and related materials for various events and venues.
      - Group 16, 1952-2007 (Box-folder 59/5)
        See the description for box-folder 59/4.
      - Group 17, 1964-2005 (Box-folder 59/6)
      - Group 18, 1950-2004 (Box-folder 60/1)
      - Group 19, 1950-2002 (Box-folder 60/2)
      - Group 20, 1953-1979 (Box-folder 60/3)
        Programs from the English Folk Dance and Song Society Festival (1953; with Jean's handwritten notes), the National Folk Festival (1961), the Newport Folk Festival (1968), Grossinger's National Entertainment Conference (1973), Ocean County College Fine and Performing Arts (1975-1976), "Sing America Sing" (1976), the Philadelphia Folk Festival (1977), and a calendar/scrapbook for McCabe's (1979).
      - Group 21, 1983-1989 (Box-folder 60/4)
        Programs from Vancouver Folk Music Festival (1983), liner notes from "Relics and Treasure: Uncle Charlie Osborne" (1985), Cumberland College Centennial Homecoming Gala Celebration (1988), and Song of Kentucky State Tour (1989).
      - Group 22, 1990-2007 (Box-folder 60/5)
        Programs from the 23rd annual Kent State Folk Festival (1990), People's Poetry Gathering (2003), White River Folk Festival (2004), and Roots Music and Arts Festival (2007). Also included is an issue of Luckenbach Moon (vol. 8, issue 4; April 2002).
      - Group 23, 2003 (Box-folder 60/6)
        A wood and paper "church fan," promoting the NEA National Heritage Fellows from Appalachia evening concert series.
      - Group 24, 1975, 1985, undated (Box-folder 60/7)
      - Group 25, 1960-1969 (Box-folder 61/1)
        Three hand-painted small posters advertising a Jean Ritchie performance, as presented by The Spinners (the English folk group); likely in reference to their TV show in the early 1960s.
      - Group 26 (Box-folder 61/2)
        A poster for the East Tennessee State University (1969), posters for the Fox Hollow Festival (circa 1971; 1972), a poster advertising a fundraising concert for The Mountain Eagle (undated), and a poster with inventory and price lists, from the Susan Reed and James Karen Antique Shop (undated).
      - Group 27, circa 1959-1975, undated (Box-folder 61/3)
        Posters and announcements for the following events: Second annual Festival of Contemporary Music (1959), A and S Elektra Folk Song Festival of Stars (possibly 1962), 13th annual Fall Festival (John C. Campbell Folk School, Brasstown, NC; possibly 1975), retirement recognition dinner honoring 40 years of service by Frank M. Warner, and Swapping Song Fair (undated).
      - Group 28, 1963-2001, undated (Box-folder 61/4)
        Posters, flyers, and related ephemera.
      - Group 29, 1976-1997, undated (Box-folder 61/5)
        See the description for box-folder 61/4.
      - Group 30, 1959-2000 (Box-folder 62)
        Oversized items, including posters, certificates, and related materials
  - Subseries 3: Writings
    Most of the writings are by Jean but also included are documents she edited (most notably Newport Folk Festival Songbook) plus works edited by others that either include Jean's writings, or honor her in some other way.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Song notes
      - Repertoire - Ritchie Family (1/2) (Box-folder 63/1)
        Typed lyrics, handwritten note scraps, transcribed music, with lyrics in the handwriting of Abigail Ritchie (Jean's mother), and noted as such.
      - Repertoire - Ritchie Family (2/2) (Box-folder 63/2)
        See the description for box-folder 63/1.
      - Jason Ritchie and related information, 1949 (Box-folder 63/3)
        Typed transcript of Jean's conversation with Jason Ritchie (seems incomplete), handwritten lyrics, transcribed music, one photocopy of a typed lyrics, and 3 dittos of typed lyrics handwritten notes.
      - Words to songs for the Jean Ritchie Songbook (1/2), 1950-1997, undated (Box-folder 63/4)
      - Jean Ritchie Songbook (2/2), 1950-1997, undated (Box-folder 63/5)
      - Party Notes (parties past, addresses, etc.), 1962, undated (Box-folder 63/6)
      - Scotland and England, 1980 (Box-folder 63/7)
        Correspondence and handwritten notes.
      - Song list master, 1964, undated (Box-folder 63/8)
        Correspondence, and typed and handwritten lists of published songs.
      - Work in progress by Jean Ritchie (1/2), 1964, 1975, undated (Box-folder 63/9)
      - Work in progress by Jean Ritchie (2/2), 1964, 1975, undated (Box-folder 64/1)
      - Notes and drafts, 1950-1969 (Box-folder 64/2)
        Handwritten notes, lyrics, and musical notation.
      - Song words, group 1 (1/2), 1952-1967 (Box-folder 64/3)
        Handwritten and typed lyrics, a list of folk song sources, a list of songs for camp, newspaper clippings from the column "Greetings," by Allan M. Trout, transcribed music, and related materials [item in oversize].
      - Song words, group 1 (2/2), 1952-1967 (Box-folder 64/4)
        See the description for box-folder 64/3.
      - Song words, group 2 (Box-folder 64/5)
        Handwritten and typed lyrics, and lyrics and music photocopied and printed from published sources.
      - New songs (original scribbles), 1966-2003, undated (Box-folder 64/6)
        Typed and handwritten lyrics, with edits; correspondence from 1966, 1971, 1980, and 2003. Some lyrics noted as "sung by Jason Ritchie." The folder name is from Jean's original folder.
      - Set lists: South Carolina, Kentucky, and Tennessee (Box-folder 64/7)
        The original folder header was "Hindman notes," but most of the contents of this folder are set lists from performances in South Carolina, with set lists, receipts, and other materials from Kentucky, Tennessee, and possibly elsewhere.
      - Song ideas - current, 1959, 1964, undated (Box-folder 64/8)
      - Song birthings: poems, tunes, ideas, 1959-1979 (Box-folder 64/9)
        Handwritten and typed lyrics, poems, and notes.
      - Songs and poems - work in progress (Box-folder 64/10)
        Handwritten and typed lyrics and poetry. Photocopied poetry in an envelope postmarked 2004. Some of the contents in this folder were written by Jean, some by others, and some unattributed.
      - Song lyrics and poems, 1940-1970, undated (Box-folder 64/11)
        Typed lyrics and poems, almost all of which were written or adapted by Jean, one attributed to John Hall (one of Jean's pseudonym), 'Than Hall (another one of Jean's pseudonyms), a list of tunes on transcription tape The date range reflects when the works were originally written.
      - Morning Sing, 1997, undated (Box-folder 65/1)
        Handwritten, typed, and photocopied lyrics and poems, some of them written by Jean, and others noted as traditional; a tribute to Jean's sister Edna, and various other documents and writings, along with a Hindman Settlement School folder.
      - Songs, 1950-1969 (Box-folder 65/2)
        Lyrics, poems, and music, variously handwritten, typed, photocopied, and dittoed. Works by Jean, A.C. Ritchie, Jason Ritchie, and others. Includes a copy of Northcountrie Broadsheet Balladrie, no. 5: "Lament for Albert."
      - Poems, 1950-2001, undated (Box-folder 65/3)
        Typed and handwritten poems, letters, envelopes, notes, lyrics
      - Song notes, 1960-1979 (Box-folder 65/4)
        Typed and handwritten lyrics, poems, notes, and song lists. One sheet of transcribed music.
      - "For J.R." - poems, songs, etc., 1970-1996 (Box-folder 65/5)
        Creative works written in honor of Jean, plus correspondence, and a photocopy of the music for "An Appalachian Folk Songfest." The folder also includes an issue of Mountain Live and Work magazine (July-August 1970).
      - Correspondence and other materials (1/2), 1962-2006 (Box-folder 65/6)
        Correspondence, clippings, poetry, a copy of "Songs to Live By," transcribed music and copies of printed music, Jean's high school graduation ceremony program (in the shape of a tulip), National Health Service cards for Jonathan and Peter Pickow, and other ephemera. Photos and negatives have been moved to Series 3. Materials in box-folder 65/6 and box-folder 65/7 were received by AFC without any arrangement.
      - Correspondence and other materials (2/2), 1962, 1999 (Box-folder 65/7)
        Letters, lyrics, emails, notes, songbook, music score. See the description for box-folder 65/6
      - Songs sent to performers, 1965, undated (Box-folder 65/8)
      - Children's music and games, circa 1979 (Box-folder 65/9)
        A list of songs, possibly for a program or recording.
    - Sub-subseries 2: Books, magazines, and recordings
      Most of these materials are drafts, galleys, proofs, early versions, etc.
      - Early notes (Box-folder 66/1)
        Handwritten notes, lyrics, and music transcriptions.
      - Writings, 1952-1971, undated (Box-folder 66/2)
        Handwritten and typed poetry, lyrics, and notes, and typed biographical narratives Jean wrote about herself and her family (possibly a draft form later published).
      - Writings, notes, and research, 1957, undated (Box-folder 66/3)
      - Articles (1/2), 1954-1968 (Box-folder 66/4)
        Drafts and proofs of articles, as well as notes for potential articles and photo essays, including "Ballad-hunting in the British Isles," an essay on folk song collecting in Cork, Ireland, a photo essay for Cosmopolitan magazine, "The Dogs of Great St. Bernard Today" (written by George Pickow), a crayon illustration for the cover of "Mystery with Mother Goose" plus another crayon illustration, a handwritten draft of the story by Jean, a typed essay by Jean called "Sorghum Making," plus correspondence and other documents.
      - Articles (2/2), 1954-1968 (Box-folder 66/5)
        See the description for box-folder 66/4. Also includes a copy of "Over to you," a BBC publication for schools (Autumn term 1968).
      - Vague magazine, vol. 1, no. 1, 1946 (Box-folder 66/6)
        A quarterly publication of the Xi Chapter of Chi Delta Phi (sorority), at University of Kentucky, Lexington. Jean's first published poem appeared in this issue.
      - "Living is collecting: growing up in a Southern Appalachian 'folk' family," circa 1977 (Box-folder 66/7)
        A paper written by Ritchie and delivered at a conference. Also included in the book An Appalachian Symposium: Essays Written in Honor of Cratis D. Williams
      - Correspondence and a book cover, 1889, 1968 (Box-folder 66/8)
        An item of correspondence to Jean, regarding publication of a story she wrote, to be published in Country Magazine (September 1968), and the cover for Father Kemp's old folks' concert music (the cover reads The old folks' concert tunes), from the 1889 edition.
      - Paper fragment, undated (Box-folder 66/9)
        A small fragment of paper found with book manuscripts. It is handwritten in blue ink.
      - Book proposals, circa 1950s (Box-folder 66/10)
        Eight pages of book proposals; one describes a book that became The garland of mountain song (published in 1953).
      - Drafts for publications, flyers, etc., 1951-1987, undated (Box-folder 66/11)
        Typed drafts of promotional biographical materials, tracings of photographic images of Jean, a newspaper clippings, handwritten notes, and related ephemera.
      - Henry Z. Walck, Inc., 1957-1973 (Box-folder 66/12)
        Various portions and drafts of Loves me, loves me not, which would be published as Apple seeds and soda straws; correspondence, royalty statements, and an invoice from Henry Z. Walck, Inc. (publisher), and related documents.
      - The garland of mountain song: drafts and related documents, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 66/13)
        Published in 1953, an early version was called The Jean Ritchie song book. Drafts, notes, part of a BMI statement stub, lists of titles, and related documents, including notations about copyrights transferred to Jean.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: early research, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 66/14)
        Published in 1955, with illustrations by Maurice Sendak. Handwritten and typed documents. Includes a letter from Jean to an unidentified person named John, describing the whipping story detailed in the book.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: beginnings, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/1)
        Early portion of typed script for the film, plus a film report, a letter from Hally Wood (1950), a handwritten song list, and related documents.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: early manuscript, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/2)
        Typed notes with manuscript edits, and handwritten notes.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: early work, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/3)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: beginnings and revisions) (1/2), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/4)
        Typed manuscript pages with handwritten edits.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: beginnings and revisions) (2/2), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/5)
        See the description for box-folder 67/1.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: manuscript checked; to be retyped (1/2), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/6)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: manuscript checked; to be retyped (2/2), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 67/7)
        See the description for box-folder 67/6.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: first typed manuscript (1/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/1)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: first typed manuscript (2/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/2)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: first typed manuscript (3/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/3)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: first typed manuscript (4/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/4)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: second typed manuscript (1/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/5)
        Typed manuscript pages with modest amount of handwritten edits. "Ritchie music illustrated copy" was the header for the original folder. It has neither music transcriptions nor illustrations.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: second typed manuscript (2/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/6)
        See the description for box-folder 68/5.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: second typed manuscript (3/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/7)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: second typed manuscript (4/4), 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/8)
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: illustrations by Maurice Sendak, 1954, 1988 (Box-folder 68/9)
        Copies of illustrations on coated paper, a letter from Jean to Janice Vanderpool at University of Kentucky Press, regarding rights to the illustrations, and a typed copy (with handwritten edits) of "The River Way to Jackson" (formerly called "The Drowsy Sleeper").
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: page proofs, etc., 1955 (Box-folder 68/10)
        Six pages of proofs, and part of a typed script for the film of "Singing Family," with handwritten notes.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: galleys, 1950-1959 (Box-folder 68/11)
        Galley marked with sticky notes to indicate this is a duplicate set, not to be returned, and a task list regarding details pertaining to the upcoming publication.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: material returned from Hally Wood, September 1960 (Box-folder 69/1)
        Typed lyrics, handwritten notes, and handwritten music.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: 25th Anniversary review letter and responses, circa 1954-1981 (Box-folder 69/2)
        Correspondence, a photocopy of a published review, a few handwritten notes, and two mock-ups for publicity (possibly advertisements), probably from the 1950s.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: reprint quote and copyright renewal, 1980, 1983 (Box-folder 69/3)
        Correspondence, a registration renewal form, and handwritten notes.
      - Singing family of the Cumberlands: a partial translation (Box-folder 69/4)
        A typed translation of Chapter One into Faroese, by David R. Margolin.
      - The dulcimer book: manuscript, 1961, undated (Box-folder 69/5)
        First published in 1963. Typed sections of the manuscript, plus correspondence. Photographic materials relocated to Series 3.
      - The dulcimer book: notes and correspondence (Box-folder 69/6)
        Correspondence, a questionnaire, typed and handwritten notes and writings, the published score for the arrangement of "I Celebrate Life," and mockups of the covers for The dulcimer book and for Old Bangum, and related documents.
      - Swapping song book: manuscript (Box-folder 69/7)
        First published in 1964 and again in 1999. Typed manuscript with handwritten edits.
      - Swapping song book: proofs (Box-folder 69/8)